New York State Department of Labor Minimum Wage Board Records 5381
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State Department of Labor Minimum Wage Board Records
1935-1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State Department of Labor
5381
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Minutes (administrative records), records (documents).
Minutes and reports of New York State Minimum Wage Boards for the industries of hotels, restaurants, retail trade, laundry and cleaning service, amusement and leisure, confectionery and beauty service.
2295988
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 23, 2006
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
New York State enacted its first minimum wage law in 1933 as one of the measures to combat the depression. It applied to women and minors, and minimum wage rates were established for laundry service, hotel and restaurant employees. The law was declared unconstitutional by the state Court of Appeals, and the decision was later upheld by the Supreme Court of the United States. Later, the Supreme Court upheld a minimum wage law enacted by the state legislature of Washington, and in 1937, New York State adopted a second minimum wage law. This law declared it was the public policy of the State of New York that women and minors employed in any occupation should receive wages sufficient to provide them with adequate maintenance to protect their health.
The law provided that the Industrial Commissioner at his own discretion, or upon a petition from 50 or more residents, could initiate an investigation to learn whether the wages being paid in a particular occupation were sufficient to provide adequate maintenance. Based upon his findings, the Commissioner could appoint a wage board composed of three public, three employee and three employer representatives. The economics data prepared by the Labor Department on conditions in the industry, wages for similar jobs in other industries, and the cost of living were to be used by the Board.
The Board was required to hold public hearings, after due notice to all interested parties, to gather additional data. After the hearings, the Board discussed the data in private hearings and recommends a minimum wage based on the following criteria established by the law: an amount sufficient to provide adequate maintenance, the value of the service or class of service rendered, and wages paid in the state for work of like or comparable character. On an average each Board met for about a six month period. With its recommendations for a minimum wage, it submitted a report and the transcript of the public hearings to the Industrial Commissioner. The Commissioner held public hearings on the rate and then issue a minimum wage order, allowing the industry ninety days to comply with the order.
In 1944 the law was amended to cover men as well as women and children. In 1947 the period for compliance was reduced from 90 to 60 days. The policy of the State Labor Department was to apply the law primarily to industries not covered by the Federal Wage and Hour Law. By 1956 about 1,260,000 workers were covered by state minimum wage orders. The first industries to be covered were laundry, beauty service and confectionery in 1938. The cleaning and dyeing industry was covered in 1939 and hotels and restaurants in 1940. As the cost of living rose, additional boards were appointed to make new recommendations for these industries. A wage board number was assigned consecutively to each industry as the Board was appointed, eleven industries or occupations were covered by 1962. The additional boards in each group were then assigned a letter, i.e., the wage order 1-D in the laundry service group would indicate that there have been five boards in the laundry industry.
Scope and Contents
Summary: Consist chiefly of minutes and reports of New York State Minimum Wage Boards for the industries of hotels, restaurants, retail trade, laundry and cleaning service, amusement and leisure, confectionery and beauty service.
Files consist of the minutes of the public hearings of the New York State Minimum Wage Boards; the hearings before the industrial commissioner on the following industries: laundry and cleaning service, beauty service, confectionery, restaurant, and hotel (1947) and the amusement and leisure industries (1950-1951); and mandatory Board orders governing minimum wage standards in the hotel industry (1948), amusement and leisure industry (1951), laundry and cleaning industries (1947) and retail trade (1951).
Additionally, reports of the Boards for the laundry and cleaning industry (1933, 1938), the confectionery industry (1942), the hotel and restaurant industries (1935), and the amusement and leisure industry (1950-1951), as well as reports of the commissioner on the laundry and cleaning industry (1933, 1938), retail trade (1945) and the hotel and restaurant industries (1939-1940).
Also legal documents (briefs, opinions, decisions and resolutions) pertaining to cases appealed before the New York State Board of Standards and Appeals regarding Minimum Wage Board mandatory orders to the laundry and cleaning industry (1939), the restaurant and hotel industries (1941) and retail trade (1946) as well as a dissent by Eugene Foley (member, Retail Trade Minimum Wage Board) on a 1945 Board report to the industrial commissioner.
Finally, reports of the New York State Division of Industrial Relations on wages and hours of work in the N.Y. laundry and cleaning services industry (1937-1945), and on the operation of the retail trade minimum wage order in N.Y. (1945-1947) and of the Women's Trade Union League on conditions of women workers in the hotel and restaurant industry (n.d.)
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5179 mf: New York State Department of Labor, Minimum Wage Board, Laundry and Beauty Industry Minutes on Microfilm 6152: New York State Department of Labor Files 6291: New York State Department of Labor Benefits Files
Women -- Employment -- United States.; Hours of labor. Laundry industry. New York (State); Wages. Cleaning and dyeing industry. New York (State); Wages. Confectionery industry. New York (State); Wages. Hotels, taverns, etc. New York (State).; Wages. Laundry industry. New York (State); Wages. Minimum wage. New York (State); Wages. Recreation industry. New York (State); Wages. Restaurants, lunch rooms, etc. New York (State); Wages. Retail trade. New York (State); Wages. Women. New York (State); Working conditions. Hotels, taverns, etc. New York (State).; Working conditions. Restaurants, lunch rooms, etc. New York (State).; New York (State). Department of Labor.; New York (State). Division of Industrial Relations.; New York (State). Retail Trade Minimum Wage Board.; National Women's Trade Union League of America.; Foley, Eugene
2295988
- Beauty Service Volume I, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Binder
- The Laundry Industry Volume I, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Laundry Industry Volume II, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Minimum Wage - Laundry Industry, 1933-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Laundry Industry Volume III, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Conditions of Women Workers in the Hotel & Restaurant Industry Findings (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Report of the Industrial Commissioner to the Hotel & Restaurant Wage Board, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Beauty Service Volume II, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Beauty Service Volume III, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Report of the Industrial Commissioner to the Cleaning & Dyeing Wage Board, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- The Cleaning & Dyeing Industry Volume I, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The Cleaning & Dyeing Industry Volume II, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- The Confectionery Industry, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Restaurant Min. Wage Board, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Restaurant Industry Vol. II, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Verbatim Minutes of the Meetings of the Restaurant Minimum Wage Board, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Restaurant Industry Volume IV, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Restaurant Industry. Minutes of Meetings & Public Hearings, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Report of the Industrial Commissioner to the Hotel Minimum Wage Board Volume I, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Report of the Industrial Commissioner to the Hotel Minimum Wage Board Volume II, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- The Hotel Industry Volume I, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The Hotel Industry Volume II, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Hotel Industry Volume III, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Amusement & Recreation. Minimum Wage Board Vol. 1, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Amusement & Recreation. Minimum Wage Board Vol. II, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Retail Trade Min. Wage Board, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 4)